# Siqi Wu

Ann Arbor, MI, USA | siqiwu@umich.edu | https://avalanchesiqi.github.io/

### RESEARCH SUMMARY

I aim to derive principles for responsible social systems, with my core expertise in large-scale quantitative analysis and collaboration with experts in social science, communication, and political science. I work towards my goal through a variety of methods – from curating large social media datasets, to modeling collective user behavior, to building algorithmic audit, to designing and testing new crowdsourcing systems.

#### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

# Research Fellow | University of Michigan. Ann Arbor, MI, USA

2021.01 - present

- Center for Social Media Responsibility. Advisor: Paul Resnick

Projects include (1) measuring cross-partisan discussions on YouTube; (2) characterizing concept difference and (3) quantifying the impacts of annotator demographics in labeling hate, offensive, and toxic social media content; (4) calibrating prevalence estimation methods for online problematic speech; (5) designing effective training procedure for crowdsourced labeling; (6) auditing polarized recommendations in YouTube recommender system.

# Research Fellow | Australian National University. Canberra, ACT, Australia

2020.09 - 2021.03

- Computational Media Lab. Advisor: Lexing Xie

Projects include (1) measuring collective human attention across different social platforms; (2) picturing global media consumption during COVID-19.

# Software Engineer | MicroStrategy, Inc. Hangzhou, Zhejiang, China

2015.09 - 2016.05

- Big Data Engine team. Built Apache Spark alike engine to process massive data.

# Software Developer Intern | Baidu, Inc. Beijing, China

2014.12 - 2015.02

- Baidu Maps team. Developed a tool to collect real time traffic status.

# **EDUCATION**

### Australian National University. Canberra, ACT, Australia

2016.06 - 2021.04

- PhD in Computer Science. Advisor: Lexing Xie
- Thesis: Measuring collective attention in online content: Sampling, engagement, and network effects

# University of Melbourne. Melbourne, VIC, Australia

2013.07 - 2015.07

- Master of Information Technology. Advisor: Richard Sinnott
- Thesis: An architecture for big data processing and visualisation of traffic data

# Tianjin University. Tianjin, China

2008.09 - 2012.06

- Bachelor of Electronics Engineering. Advisor: Yugong Wu

#### **AWARDS**

- AAAI ICWSM Best Senior Program Committee '22, '23
- AAAI ICWSM Spotlight Paper '21
- ACM CSCW Best Paper Honorable Mention '19
- Google PhD Fellowship '18

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

- \* Equal authorship
- 14. How to train your YouTube recommender to avoid unwanted videos
  - Liu, **Wu**, and Resnick. *ICWSM* '24. Full paper
- 13. The shapes of the fourth estate during the pandemic: Profiling COVID-19 news consumption in eight countries
  - Yang, Xie, and Wu. CSCW '23. Full paper
- 12. Prevalence estimation in social media using black box classifiers
  - Wu and Resnick. ICWSM '23. Tutorial
- 11. Just another day on Twitter: A complete 24 hours of Twitter data Pfeffer et al. *ICWSM* '23. Dataset paper
- 10. Whose advantage? Measuring attention dynamics across YouTube and Twitter on controversial topics Lee\*, **Wu**\*, Ertugrul\*, Lin, and Xie. *ICWSM* '22. Full paper
- 9. Cross-partisan discussions on YouTube: Conservatives talk to liberals but liberals don't talk to conservatives **Wu** and Resnick. *ICWSM* '21. Full paper, spotlight paper (top 8)
- 8. AttentionFlow: Visualising influence in networks of time series Shin\*, Tran\*, **Wu**\*, Mathews, Wang, Lyall, and Xie. *WSDM* '21. Demo paper
- 7. Unsupervised cyberbullying detection via time-informed Gaussian mixture model Cheng, Shu, **Wu**, Silva, Hall, and Liu. *CIKM* '20. Full paper
- 6. Variation across scales: Measurement fidelity under Twitter data sampling **Wu**, Rizoiu, and Xie. *ICWSM* '20. Full paper
- 5. Estimating attention flow in online video networks
  - Wu, Rizoiu, and Xie. CSCW '19. Full paper, best paper honorable mention (top 5%)
- 4. How is attention allocated? Data-driven studies of popularity and engagement in online videos **Wu.** WSDM '19. Doctoral consortium
- 3. Beyond views: Measuring and predicting engagement in online videos
  - Wu, Rizoiu, and Xie. ICWSM '18. Full paper
- 2. Will this video go viral? Explaining and predicting the popularity of YouTube videos Kong, Rizoiu, **Wu**, and Xie. WWW '18. Demo paper
- 1. SMASH: A cloud-based architecture for big data processing and visualization of traffic data **Wu**, Morandini, Sinnott. *DSDIS* '15. Full paper

# **TEACHING**

- Teaching assistant in ANU graduate course COMP6490 Document Analysis ('17, '18)
- Teaching assistant in ANU undergraduate course COMP1030 Art of Computing ('17)

# **STUDENTS**

- Alexander Liu (UMich PhD)
- Zain Padamsee (Bowdoin College undergrad)
- Cai Yang (ANU undergrad) → Saarland University/Max Planck Institute

#### **SERVICES**

- ICWSM '23 poster, demo, and dataset track co-chair
- ICWSM '22 student volunteer and scholarship chair

- Senior program committee: ICWSM ('22 '24)
- Conference program committee/reviewer: WebSci ('22 '24), CSCW ('19 '23), TheWebConf ('19, '20, '23), ICIS ('22, '23), IC2S2 ('23), CIKM ('23), ASONAM ('21, '22), ICWSM ('17, '18, '21), AAAI ('19)
- Ad hoc journal reviewer: EPJ Data Science, Collective Intelligence, Social Science Computer Review, ACM Transactions on Information Systems

# MISC.

- Organizing: co-organized the Computational Media Lab winter workshop '19
- Running: 20 100+km events, 60+ (ultra) marathons finisher, 2:42 marathoner